S2 Module 5: Small Fields, Binary Fields with Jim Posen
Nico: Welcome to this Module
of the ZK Whiteboard Sessions.
I am Nico and I'll be today's host.
And with me I have Jim from Irreducible.
Jim: Thanks, Nico. It's great to be here.
Today we're going to talk about small field
SNARKs and why this line of work is important.
We're going to start with some motivating factors
and talk about the performance efficiency
that we can get using small field techniques.
Then we're going to go through an example
of how to construct a STARK-like Plonky2
that uses the Goldilocks 64-bit field.
And finally, we're going to talk about
some recent work that investigates
how small we can make our
fields using binary towers.
How does that sound?
Nico: Yeah. Sounds great.
Jim: Let's jump in.
Nico: Yeah.
So you said motivation first.
Why would we want to do small field?
What do we even mean by small?
Jim: Oh, I'm glad you asked!
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: This really contrasts with the default way
that we had of constructing SNARKs prior
to, let's say, the Plonky2 project,
which really popularized this.
And before that, we would typically use a
finite field that is a 256-bit prime number.
This is for a few reasons,
but one of them is this appears in secure elliptic
curves as the field that we want to work in.
And also we can recall that a lot of SNARKs
are based on polynomial identity testing.
And when we do a randomized
polynomial identity test,
the false acceptance probability,
which is what we're trying to minimize,
is inversely proportional
to the size of our field.
And so if we use a really
large field that's 256 bits,
we get a very small and
acceptable error probability.
Now, the problem with these is the
performance of field multiplications
is much larger with 256 bit
numbers than with smaller numbers.
One reason is, if we look at
the computational complexity,
the time it takes to do a field multiplication
is superlinear in the number of bits,
which means if I double my field size,
I need to do more than twice the work
in order to do this multiplication.
And also, computers have native
registers for smaller elements,
integer elements like 64 and 32-bit numbers.
So we want to capture that hardware efficiency.
To throw some quick numbers at you,
you can do on my computer about 60 million 256-bit
prime field multiplications
per second on a single core,
whereas it's 1,200 with the
64-bit Goldilocks field.
So that's 20 times more field multiplications
you can do with a 64-bit field.
Nico: Right.
That sounds worth it.
Jim: The other thing that we need to talk about is
when we're actually building a
SNARK, we have some sort of circuit.
And typically we need our circuit to express
the computation that we want to prove.
And the actual values that appear in
our circuit trace or on the wires,
are much smaller than the actual
size of our field elements, usually.
In a lot of computations,
we'll have very small values,
maybe 16 bits or 8 bits or even 1 bit
inside of a field that might be 256 bits.
And the rest of the bits in that
field element are just zeros.
Nico: So I'm using this sort of big storage
slot of 256 bits for just 1 bit
that I'm going to do stuff with.
Jim: Exactly.
So this seems very wasteful, right?
Both in terms of the time to
do the field multiplications,
but also the memory usage we need to pay for.
And bad memory usage leads
to bad cache utilization,
which again leads to poor performance.
So these are some of the motivating
factors for why we're interested in
building SNARKs and STARKs over small fields.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: As one --
Nico: And so, just to be clear, small means
closer to our, like, computer register size.
So like 64 bits or 32 bits or smaller.
Jim: Exactly.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: Yeah.
Let's almost by definition say that it fits
within a machine register, which is 32 or 64 bits.
One disclaimer!
I'm going to talk about the STARK protocol,
but I'm going to refer to all STARKs as SNARKs.
There's a subtle difference, but I don't
think it's worth getting into right now.
Nico: Cool.
So, yeah.
Should we run through a protocol with a
small field and see what it looks like?
Jim: Yeah, absolutely.
Let's refresh on a very simple STARK that we could
talk about, which is like a Fibonacci example.
So we're going to have, you know, our computation
trace and this is going to
be the Fibonacci numbers.
And we're actually just going to
have, for now, a single polynomial.
Nico: Okay. So a single column in our trace?
Jim: A single column in our
trace, and we'll call this f.
And this will have a number
of values and the constraint
that we want is that f at [i + 2] - (f --
Oops.
At [i + 1] + f at [i]) = 0
for all indices i.
Nico: Right.
Jim: In our table.
There are some boundary constraints that
we're going to hand wave aside for now.
Nico: So we're saying
f[i + 2] - (f[i + 1] + f[i]) = 0.
Right? So --
Jim: That's right.
Nico: Okay. Cool.
Jim: And we want that to hold for every slot.
Nico: Right.
And then do we wrap around? Are we going to --
let's just ignore it for now?
Jim: We're going to ignore what happens at
the very top and the very bottom for now.
There's some way that you
could compensate for this.
But I believe you've talked about
STARKs in a previous session
and expressed how we can turn
this into a polynomial problem.
But roughly, the way we're going to
prove this is with three steps, right?
Like first, we're going to commit.
Two, we're going to do some sort
of polynomial division check.
I'm going to call this the vanishing argument.
What we want to show is that this equation
vanishes or is equal to zero over the whole trace.
Nico: Yeah. I think we've called
it the zerocheck previously.
Jim: Okay. Let's call it that then.
The third step is the polynomial identity test,
which is how we're going to
kind of finish the zero check.
And then we need to do our FRI evaluation proof.
FRI is the Fast Reed-Solomon IOP of proximity.
I'm going to maybe refer to it as
a polynomial commitment scheme in
this lecture, or in this whiteboard session,
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: Even though there are some subtleties and --
Nico: Cool.
Jim: It serves various purposes.
Nico: I guess it fulfills that role. Right?
Jim: Exactly.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: So perhaps what we can do is let's
run through how this protocol looks
when we try to use the a 64-bit
field for the entire protocol
and see what we might need to fix.
When I talk about a 64-bit field,
I'm specifically going to refer to Goldilocks.
And this is a prime number that is 64
bits or fits within a 64-bit register.
And it has a very special structure
that makes it computationally efficient to do within
a very small number of cycles on a regular CPU.
And it's also compatible with STARK techniques
in the sense that it allows for the
Fast Fourier Transform that we need.
So let's imagine that we have this whole trace.
All of our numbers are integers that are sort
of embedded within this Goldilocks field.
And we want to commit this.
This works with no problems.
Nico: Okay
Jim: So what does committing look like?
Well, we're going to apply an
error-correcting code, the Reed-Solomon code,
and then we're going to build
a Merkle tree and we can --
Nico: So is this, you know, the
interpolation and the blow up?
Jim: Exactly.
Nico: Okay. Cool.
Jim: Yes.
And this works perfectly over
this Goldilocks prime field.
The next step is --
Nico: I guess, unless we take our Fibonacci
sequence into like way, way, way too big numbers
which don't fit in here, right?
Jim: That's right. Yes.
Nico: Okay. Cool.
As long as we're working with like 0,
1, and then, et cetera, we're fine.
Jim: Yeah. It would take, I guess --
Yes. That's right.
As long as our Fibonacci number stays
within this field, we're pretty happy.
The next is the zerocheck.
And I'm not going to write
this out sort of completely,
but we'll remember that, this is
basically a polynomial identity test.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: Where what we want to do is we have
-- you know, this is our constraint,
and we want to say something like the
composition, which is this constraint,
applied to f over a formal variable x,
is divisible by the polynomial
that is zero everywhere
and of appropriate degree.
And we're actually going to check
this with the multiplication.
So we're going to have the
prover provide a quotient Q,
and this is the zero polynomial.
And we want to do this polynomial identity check.
And if this is satisfied, then we know
that this is zero over the entire trace.
Nico: Is this what people
call the "vanishing polynomial"?
Jim: This is the vanishing polynomial.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: Exactly.
Now, what we need to do in the zero
check step is compute this quotient Q.
The way we do this is, we evaluate the
polynomial at an extended, or over some domain,
that is where we're not going to
get division by zero elements.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: We're going to do all of our
point divisions in this other domain,
and then we're going to interpolate
that polynomial to get our quotient Q.
Nico: Cool.
We being the prover.
Jim: We being the prover.
Nico: The verifier doesn't do any of this. Right?
Jim: That's right.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: Good point.
The prover is going to do all this work and
provide commitments to the
quotient, to the verifier.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: And what I want to observe is that
we are also able to do this entire process
of computing the quotient Q for a single
constraint over our Goldilocks prime.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: Now, when we get into the FRI evaluation,
this is where we're going to do our
randomized polynomial identity test.
Nico: Yes.
Jim: So what we want to do is we want to pick --
the verifier chooses, you know, an element Z,
which is a random element from our field,
and we want to check that this relation
holds at this specific point Z.
Nico: That's our zerocheck.
Jim: This is --
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: Yes.
Nico: I think lecture -- maybe the second module.
Cool.
Jim: Now, the security of this is
based on the Schwartz–Zippel lemma.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: And without writing that out
completely, what we know is that
there is a error probability or a essentially
it guarantees us a false acceptance probability
that's inversely proportional
to the size of the field.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: This is where we will
start to run into a problem
because the size of our field is only 2^64
and really we want an error probability
that's less than say 2^128
or something much smaller.
Nico: Are those the bits of
security that we talk about?
Jim: Yes.
That is what we --
That is sort of by definition what we
need to achieve a 128-bit security target.
Nico: Okay.
And we're not even close right now.
Jim: We're not even close. We're --
Nico: Okay.
Jim: That's right.
We would need a much bigger
field, like a 256-bit prime field
that we sort of were trying to replace
in the first place in order to get this.
This Schwartz–Zippel test to give
us an acceptable security level.
So we now need to talk about
how we're going to fix this
with a technique called error amplification.
So we're going to talk about how we're going to
use error amplification to
use the Goldilocks field,
but still get a very small error probability
which is achieving a 128-bit security level.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: There are a few techniques to do this,
but I'm going to talk about
using extension fields.
Nico: Okay. What are those?
Jim: Extension fields, you might actually already
be aware of from high school algebra, where --
Do you remember learning about the
complex numbers and the imaginary numbers?
Nico: Yep.
Jim: Great.
So the idea was that we had the real number line,
and we can think of in our analogy, the reals
kind of being like our Goldilocks number.
And what we did was we said,
we're going to declare that a complex
number has the form a + bi,
where i is the imaginary unit.
And this basically turns our number
system into a two-dimensional plane,
where a is along the real axis
and b is along the imaginary axis.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: And now, any of our numbers
falls somewhere in this plane.
The other thing is, we knew that
we declared that i² = 1.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: Sorry, -1.
Nico: Yes.
Jim: We declared that i² = -1.
We can do something analogous
with the Goldilocks prime.
In fact, what we --
What the complex numbers are, are they
are an extension field of the real field.
Nico: Right. Okay.
Jim: And what this means is, an extension,
we're going to talk about a
degree 2 extension of Goldilocks,
meaning we're going to have
a two-dimensional plane
and every point in our extension field
is a pair of Goldilocks field elements.
Nico: Right.
Jim: Now, this means that the size
of our field can gets squared.
If we count up how many coordinates
there are in a two-dimensional plane
where each value can -- is a
Goldilocks prime field element,
we have a 128-bit field or a field
with close to 2^128 elements.
Nico: I see.
Or I guess one way to say it is also every --
Yeah. How many pairs of
Goldilocks elements can we have?
Jim: Exactly.
Nico: Right. Okay.
Jim: And if we count those up, we see that it is
enough to give us a secure Schwartz–Zippel test.
Nico: Right. Right.
Jim: I want to mention a couple of properties
about extension field multiplication,
because it doesn't come for free.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: So let's remember how we
had to multiply complex numbers.
If we took two different complex
numbers, (a + bi) * (c + di),
and we want to compute this,
there are a few cross terms.
Nico: We are gonna have to
distribute this out. Yeah.
Jim: We have to distribute this out.
So we get ac + --
Nico: Oh, this takes me back!
Jim: And at this point, when we multiply, we're
going to remember that i² = -1.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: But the thing I want to point out is that
to do this multiplication of two elements,
we actually had to do four different
multiplications of our base field elements.
Nico: Yes.
Jim: So doubling the size of our field and
operating on pairs turned into four cross terms.
Again, this is an example of how
when you increase your field size,
it's a super linear growth in
the multiplication complexity.
Nico: That makes sense.
Jim: I want to mention one more property which is
if we want to scale a Goldilocks
field by a base field element.
So in this case --
Nico: Sorry. Scale an
extension field by base field?
Jim: Yes.
Nico: Okay. Cool.
Jim: I want to point out that if we want to scale
an extension field element
by a base field element.
So instead of multiplying an
extension field by an extension field,
we multiply a base times an extension field.
This requires fewer multiplications.
So if we took s * (a + bi), we can
simply distribute this to be sa + --
Nico: sbi. Okay.
Jim: So as much as possible, we would like to
operate with multiplications in the base field,
and the next best thing is to multiply base
field elements by extension field elements.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: But when necessary, we have
a way of multiplying extension
field elements by extension field elements.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: I think at this point, we
can return to the "how we're
going to run the STARK protocol
using the Goldilocks extension."
Nico: Sounds good.
So back to a STARK.
Jim: Let's go back to the STARK.
Let's start over.
So we have our trace with the column f,
and we're going to keep this
inside of the Goldilocks field.
These are not extension field elements yet.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: And the first thing we did was commit.
Nico: So the reason we can do this is because
we're working with just small numbers. Right?
Things that are less than 2^64?
Jim: Exactly.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: Yeah.
We, for this purpose, don't need --
We can fit within this field,
and also we know that every
Goldilocks field element is
itself living within the extension field.
If you think about the real number
line that lives within the plane.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: So the first thing we want
to do is commit our column f.
And I claim that we can do this
the same way we did before.
We're going to do our Fast Fourier
Transform and our Reed-Solomon encoding,
and our Merkle tree building
all over the Goldilocks prime.
And this is great, because even though the
rest of our protocol might have some changes,
we still get the efficiency gain here.
Nico: Cool! So we still save on --
Yeah. Having small numbers in smaller
storage locations rather than like 256-bit?
Jim: Exactly.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: So another important thing here is that,
when we do our Fast Fourier Transform,
minimizing the memory usage of this
is really important for performance
because it means it can fit in a smaller cache.
Nico: Right. Cool.
Jim: The second step was the zerocheck.
Nico: This is where things broke down. Right?
Jim: Almost --
Nico: Or I guess with the sampling.
Jim: That's right.
So there's actually two phases here.
There's the quotient computation,
and right, this is where we just computed
the coefficients of our Q polynomial.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: The coefficients are still
within the Goldilocks base field
when we have this one constraint,
which means that the work to do
this, which is quite a bit of work,
and quite a bit of polynomial evaluations,
we can still do over our base field.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: The point where this broke
is when we did our random testing.
Random --
And at this point, we're
going to do the same thing,
but when we take z, it's going to be
basically a pair of Goldilocks elements.
It's going to be --
Nico: An element of the extension?
Jim: An element of the extension.
Nico: Amazing. Okay.
Jim: And kind of remarkably, we
can plug that in to our equations
where each of these coefficients
are from the Goldilocks field
and still do this polynomial identity test
and now get a much lower
false acceptance probability.
So we've amplified the
probability of catching an error.
Nico: So why is that?
Because we went from 1 over size of
Goldilocks to 1 over size of extension?
Jim: Yes.
Our extension field, remember,
is, you know, roughly -
I'm going to call this like GL²
for the tuples of the extension.
And this is roughly of size 2^128.
Nico: Okay.
Amazing.
Jim: Then we're going to move
on to our FRI evaluation proof,
and run the FRI protocol.
And without getting into the details of this here,
the FRI protocol will itself involve more sampling
of random elements from the
Goldilocks extension field.
But by a similar argument, we
can show that the error, that --
the soundness error that we
get during the FRI protocol is
inversely proportional roughly to our --
the size of our extension field.
And so the same soundness amplification
technique works in this step as well.
Nico: Right. But now FRI is
going to work over the extension.
Jim: Yes.
Nico: Okay. So no savings really here.
Jim: That's right.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: At this point, we're not getting savings,
but we have saved a bunch of work
here in our commitment phase,
we've saved work in -- well, in phase 2a.
And phase 2b is quite cheap to do for the prover.
And phase 3, we didn't really save any work,
but actually we're just really happy
that we saved work in the commitment
and quotient computation phases.
Nico: I mean, I remember recent
talks from Eli Ben-Sasson
who was saying these were the real bottlenecks.
Jim: That's right.
Nico: Good news.
Jim: Yeah. That's absolutely true.
The FRI protocol is linear in the
size of the extended polynomial,
whereas the commitment phase
is actually really expensive
because it involves both
the Fast Fourier Transform,
which is superlinear in
the size of the polynomial,
and also a lot of hashing
to build our Merkle trees.
So if we can even just save work in the
commitment phase, we're really happy.
Nico: So now I have another question, which is,
by the same logic, if I took something that's
64 bits and to get security, I extended it,
could I take something smaller and extend it more?
Jim: Yes.
And there's a lot of projects doing this today.
So there's two smaller prime fields
that are used by other projects.
The RISC Zero project began using
the Baby Bear prime field, which --
Nico: Do you mind writing
them out if you know them?
Jim: Yes. So let me come back over here.
So the Baby Bear field is a 31-bit prime number
and it has the form 15 * 2^27 + 1.
And we didn't talk too much
about the Fast Fourier Transform,
but it's actually really important that
we have prime numbers with this structure
that is some number times a large
power of 2 plus 1 in order to --
Nico: Oh, I guess we can
factor the 2^32 here --
Jim: Yeah. Let's do this.
Nico: Right.
Jim: Good point.
We can see that our Goldilocks
prime have this property
that we're going to call smoothness
that allows us to use the
Fast Fourier Transform techniques.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: There's another prime field --
Nico: So smoothness, just to be clear,
is the -- this thing, right?
This big 2^32 or this big power of --
Jim: It is this form where you have a
number times a big power of 2 plus 1.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: There's another prime field
that is gotten attention for --
There's a new line of work called Circle STARKs.
And this is the Mersenne field.
And this number is 2^31 - 1.
Now what do you notice?
Nico: Yeah. I mean, they don't
have the nice plus 1 thing.
Jim: It does not have the smoothness
property as I just defined it.
But due to some really creative research,
we can actually do something like the
Fast Fourier Transform for the Mersenne field,
even though it doesn't have this particular form.
And we're interested in doing this because
the computation to compute multiplications
in the Mersenne field is actually several
clock cycles cheaper than
doing it even for Baby Bear.
Nico: Wow. Okay.
I guess because it's just a
one, a bunch of zeros and --
Or maybe --
Jim: Yeah.
Nico: Oh no, not necessarily actually.
But yeah, never mind. Ignore that.
But it looks simpler.
Jim: If we were to write it out in
binary, it would be like a lot of ones.
Nico: Right.
Jim: And there's nice digital logic circuits that
could process multiplications of those numbers.
Nico: That makes sense.
Can we go even smaller?
Jim: Great question.
Actually, I forgot --
Before this, what we can do with the Baby
Bear field is we still need a field extension.
Nico: Right.
Jim: And we cannot do just a degree
2 extension, which is a plane,
because if we think about how many fields,
let's take a degree 2 extension -- Baby Bear.
I said this is a 31-bit field.
If we think about all pairs of Baby Bear elements,
we still only have less than
2^64 total elements.
And so in the case of Baby Bear and Mersenne,
we would need to use a
quartic extension, which is,
every element of our extension field is a four as
a tuple of four Baby Bear or Mersenne elements.
And there is a multiplication method
that would be defined for this.
But using basically everything that
we talked about for Goldilocks,
the rest of the STARK protocol would go through.
Nico: Right.
Amazing.
Jim: You then asked, "can we go even smaller?"
Nico: Yes.
Jim: That's a really interesting question.
And there are some challenges.
So, you know, we could ask, "could we use a
16-bit prime field or an 8-bit prime field?"
And we run into really two problems.
I'm going to erase this now.
Nico: Yeah. Sounds good.
I guess, smoothness, since you were
saying, we need this big power of 2.
Jim: That is certainly one problem. So --
And let's remember two particular phases of this.
So one was Reed-Solomon encoding.
Nico: For the commit part.
Jim: For the commit part.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: Which is part of the commitment, as you said.
And this is --
The way we implement this is
with Fast Fourier Transforms.
And the second was polynomial division.
Nico: Yes.
Jim: Which was part of our zerocheck.
Nico: Does that also need Fast Fourier Transforms?
Jim: It does.
We can reuse the Fast Fourier Transforms
that we did during the Reed-Solomon encoding.
But the property that both of these
have is that we need to take --
we need to treat our f column and
interpolate a high degree polynomial,
depending on --
relatively, we need to interpolate a polynomial
over the values that we had in our f column.
So let's say --
Nico: Like high you're saying compared to this,
but low compared to the size of
the extension field, I'm guessing.
Jim: Yes.
Nico: Because --
Okay. Cool.
Jim: So I think for typical SNARKs,
we would be talking about columns that are
in the range of 2^20 to 2^24.
That's a pretty typical size
for the height of a STARK trace.
What that means is, recall, we're going
to associate with every row in this column
a different evaluation point from our field.
Nico: Yes. The roots of unity.
Jim: Yes. The roots of unity.
Nico: Also past modules.
Jim: Now, we run into a problem if
we're trying to use a 16-bit field,
because a 16-bit field not only doesn't
even have that many roots of unity,
it doesn't even have that many points.
Nico. Right. Yes.
Jim: We couldn't possibly have 2^20
evaluation points in an 8-bit prime field.
Nico: Makes sense.
Jim: So we could use field extensions.
But this is starting to get essentially difficult,
and we're not getting the same
benefits from basically using
the efficiency of small fields when we use that.
Nico: I was going to ask. If we start
using extensions from the beginning,
we're no longer having savings like --
Jim: Exactly.
Nico: In points one and two. Okay.
Jim: So I'm going to talk about how
to solve these challenges separately.
Actually, number 2 is
potentially the easiest to solve.
And I'm not going to go into too much detail,
but recall that this was part
of our vanishing argument,
or our vanishing or zerocheck argument.
And there's another protocol that we
could replace polynomial division with
called the Sum-Check Protocol.
Nico: Right.
Jim: I believe you may have talked about
this in a past or upcoming session.
I can't -- or I'm not going
to go into the details.
But when we use the Sum-Check
Protocol for our zerocheck,
we actually don't have this limitation that
forces our field size to be very large.
We can even run the Sum-Check
Protocol with small field polynomials,
again using extension challenges.
But this all works really nicely.
Nico: Okay. So that's solved.
What about encoding?
Jim: Right. Solved with Sum-Check.
What about Reed-Solomon encoding?
Well, let's talk about quickly
what Reed-Solomon encoding is.
Reed-Solomon encoding -- Reed-Solomon is an
error-correcting code or an erasure code.
And what it effectively means is we're
going to treat our f column as a polynomial.
We're going to interpolate and
evaluate it at many more points.
So again, we have this problem that
we need lots of evaluation points
to even define what it would mean
to do a Reed-Solomon encoding.
Nico: Like even more than the trace itself?
Jim: Even more than the trace itself.
We can think about some
evaluation points down here
where we're going to extend our polynomial to.
And so, it has taken some more
creativity to get around this.
My team developed some techniques based on a
different type of field called a "binary tower".
And I want to talk about what a binary tower is
and how we can both use binary towers
and a new small field polynomial to large field
polynomial commitment scheme
reduction in some generality.
Nico: Amazing.
Jim: So have you heard of a binary field before?
Nico: I'm not sure. No.
Jim: So let's start with the smallest field
we could possibly cook up, which is F₂.
And this is literally has two elements.
It has the elements .
We're going to use our field extension technique
and create a field f₂^2
or four elements.
And we can think of these as
being pairs of F₂ elements.
Nico: Right.
So 0,0 , 0,1 , 1,0 , 1,1.
Jim: Yes.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: We can also think of this as a 2-bit string.
And we're going to just keep
doing this over and over.
Nico: Right.
Jim: And what you may have
learned in high school is that
this doesn't work for the real numbers,
but it does work for these binary fields
that we can continue to build
planes and field extensions.
So we could make a field --
Sorry. This should be 2^4.
Nico: So we're taking two of these
elements to make one of these elements.
Jim: That's right.
Nico: But because this was already
two of these, this now becomes four.
Jim: Yes.
Nico: Okay. I see. I see what's
happening. And it keep towering, right?
Jim: Yes.
So this is -- I like to think of it in terms
of the number of bits to represent each field.
So this is 4 bits.
Nico: Yeah. That's a lot less
confusing than what I was saying.
Jim: This is 8 bits.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: And we're going to just keep doing
this and we can go as high as we want.
For the purposes of this conversation, we'll
continue doing this up to f₂^128,
which is a 128-bit field.
And that is enough to give us the security
that we wanted for our Schwartz-Zippel test
and the rest of our polynomial or
our protocol soundness guarantees.
Nico: Amazing.
So you talked a bit about the costs of
multiplication in these extension fields
when we were looking at Goldilocks saying,
like, it gets more expensive as we extend more.
Is this also the case here?
Jim: This is the case that our multiplication
grows superlinearly in the number of bits.
However, there's some really
remarkable ways of constructing this.
In particular, we identified one
way of constructing this tower
that gives us really good
multiplication complexity,
matching the asymptotic complexity
of regular integer multiplication.
Nico: Wow. Okay.
Jim: And notably, what this
means is when I wrote out the
multiplication algorithm for the complex plane,
it looks like it would be a quadratic number of
multiplications you needed to do whenever
you multiplied extension field elements.
Remember that we multiplied two complex numbers
and had to do four subfield multiplications.
Actually, we can do multiplications in the
binary tower with less than a quadratic --
Nico: Okay. Super cool.
Jim: number of underlying bit
multiplications or bit operations.
So, you know, how should you think about these?
Well, again, this symbol was inclusion,
meaning we kind of have this Russian doll of
different fields that live one within another.
And whenever in our protocol we're able
to use a smaller field, we will do that.
And then whenever we require a larger
field for either more evaluation points
or for more cryptographic soundness,
we can move up to a higher tower level.
Nico: Makes sense.
So after this detour, I guess my question
is now, how does this solve that problem?
Jim: I want to talk about one more concept --
Nico: Okay. Cool.
Jim: Which is what we call packing.
And this is this notion that because
these live within it one another,
we can take -- you know,
we talked about a F₂^8 element
as being pairs of F₂^4 elements.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: And so if we have, let's say --
Where should I write this?
Nico: Should we get rid of these?
Jim: I'm going to erase this here.
In F₂, the 8 element is 8 bits.
This is the same size as 1 byte, right?
So let's say we have a bunch of bytes.
Say we have 16 of them.
I don't know if this is going
to be 16 slots, but we have --
Nico: Let's pretend.
Jim: 16 elements that are F₂^8.
Each one is a byte, so we have 16 bytes.
What I'm saying we can do is, we could
view this in many different ways.
So we could actually view this as a
single element of the 128-bit field,
or we can chunk this into 4 bytes at a time
and treat this as four 32-bit field elements.
And this is what we call packing.
It's the idea that we can take small
field elements, group them together
and treat them as big field elements.
And this doesn't say come for free,
there are technicalities we need to deal with.
But this is in general a technique that's
available to us in the setting of extension towers
that becomes really useful.
Nico: It's like kids in a trench
coat trying to get to the cinema.
Jim: Exactly!
Nico: That's what's happening here. Okay.
Jim: So I think now we're ready
to talk about how we're going to
use packing to fix our problem
with the Reed-Solomon encoding
and basically not having enough evaluation
points when we're operating over F₂.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: So the setting here
now is we have a column f.
It has 2^20 to 2^24 rows in this
column, but each element is a single bit.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: It's an F₂ element.
And we wanted some way to commit this polynomial
and run something like our STARK protocol,
but with the zerocheck replaced
with a Sum-Check reduction.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: And we also would like to
continue using Reed-Solomon codes
because they have really good properties
and they lend themselves to the FRI protocol.
Nico: Yep.
Jim: But we have this problem that
if we were to evaluate our f
column at a bunch of more points,
we could do this by padding them
up to 32-bit field elements.
So we could kind of imagine that
these all were 32-bit field elements
and we would pad with zeros.
Nico: A bunch of zeros. Okay.
Jim: But this looks really inefficient
be for all the reasons that
we didn't want to use a larger
field in the first place.
Nico: Yes.
We're back to like small things going
into a bigger field storage slot.
Jim: Right.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: So instead what we want to do is find
a way to take chunks of bits and pack them.
Nico: Trenchcoat!
Jim: Yes!
So let's imagine that we're going to
take chunks of 128 bits at a time.
128 bits here, 128 bits here,
and treat them as a single element of a
very large field of an F₂^128 field.
This is big enough for us to run FRI over.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: Now --
Nico: Does this have the
smoothness property model?
Yes. I guess, it's already --
Jim: Yeah. It has a different type of smoothness.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: And what that means is that there exists
a Fast Fourier Transform type of algorithm
that can do efficient Reed-Solomon
encoding for these binary fields.
It's called the "additive NTT".
It's slightly different from the
regular NTT or FFT that we're used to,
but it does have a notion of smoothness.
Nico: What does NTT stand for?
Jim: That's the Number Theoretic Transform.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: Which is when you --
It's a transformation on finite field vectors.
Nico: Okay.
Jim: And usually we want to refer to using
the Fast Fourier Transform algorithm,
which is famously efficient for doing this
transformation on finite field elements.
Nico: I see. Okay.
So NTT is what we want to do
and FFT is the algorithm we use.
Jim: Yes.
Nico: Cool.
Jim: So back to here, we said
that we have a column of bits.
We wanted to pack adjacent
bits into big field elements.
We wanted to use the FRI protocol
running over our big field elements
and use this to effectively evaluate the
interpolation of our column f somewhere.
Now, if we were to just do this, this
would not actually equal on its own the --
So let's talk about two different polynomials.
We have f, we have 2^20, F₂ coefficients.
And when we pack, we're going to take
chunks of 128 bits or 128 elements.
128 is 2^7.
Nico: Yeah.
Jim: And we're going to turn
-- We're going to have a --
We can define this as an
entirely different polynomial,
kind of calculate it in this way, which
is basically a memory cast on the bits.
And instead, we end up with 2^20-7.
Nico: Right.
Jim: f, 2^128 coefficients.
Because we divided our column of 2^20
into chunks of 2^7.
Jim: Exactly.
Nico: And so the division gives this. Okay.
Jim: So these are --
What I am saying is that these are
actually two separate polynomials.
They don't even have the same number of variables.
But using a Sum-Check based
reduction and a technique
that my team developed that
we call "ring switching",
what this lets us do is, if
I want the evaluation of f,
I'm going to have the prover and
verifier engage in a Sum-Check Protocol
that we call a ring switching Sum-Check.
And this is a reduction to a claim
about f hat at a particular point.
What that means is I'm then going to
get a claim about f hat at a point.
Nico: Right.
Jim: And what it means for
this to be a reduction is that
if this claim is true that f hat evaluates
to the claimed value at the claimed point,
then I should be fully convinced that f
evaluated in the way that I wanted originally.
Nico: Right.
Jim: And what's really cool here is that we
were able to do this sort of packing trick on f.
We're able to run our Reed-Solomon code over that,
because F₂^128 is smooth
and has enough evaluation points.
We were able to run the FRI protocol here,
but we were able to do a Sum-Check reduction
so that we sidestepped all the issues that
we had with using not just small fields,
but what I call tiny fields.
Nico: Right.
Jim: Fields that are way less than
the size for a machine register.
And so that explains how we're able to use
binary towers to shrink the size of our field.
Nico: So just to make sure I
understood this part correctly,
you're actually only going to commit to f hat.
Jim: That's right.
Nico: And then to get evaluations of f, I'm going
to get evaluations of f hat for my commitment.
And then there's this little protocol
that translates from f hat to f.
Jim: Yes.
Nico: Is that correct?
Okay. Cool.
Amazing.
Is that like an expensive protocol?
Is that a cheap protocol?
Jim: It's a fairly cheap protocol.
It's roughly the same cost of doing the FRI
protocol that we needed to run on f hat anyway.
Nico: Right.
Jim: So we can think of
it as being a small constant multiple, or maybe
twice as much work as we were -- we had to do.
But we're saving a lot here because instead
of running f hat for 2^20 coefficients,
we're running it for 2^20-7.
Nico: Right.
Jim: 2^13 coefficients.
Nico: So a factor of 2 here, but there's
like 7 factors of 2 removed there.
Jim: That's right.
Nico: Amazing.
Is this what people call Binius,
this sort of construction here?
Jim: Yes.
Binius refers to a project that implements all
of these techniques that my team is developing.
And it has kind of come to refer to these
techniques of using binary towers
to construct SNARKs, generally.
Nico: Amazing.
So correct me if I'm wrong, but today what we saw
is we want to use small fields for performance.
The problem with that was soundness, that
we got this one over size of field thing.
So we ended up taking
extensions to get more security.
That got us down to like 32-bit fields.
Pretty cool.
And then we were saying if
we want even smaller fields,
the problem is that we need to do FFTs
and we need our traces to be
long enough to be meaningful.
And so the solution there was -- or one
of the solutions, I guess, is packing.
Right? This idea of trenchcoat.
And to fix packing, you have
this sort of protocol here.
Jim: Exactly.
That summarizes it well.
Nico: Amazing!
Thank you very much, Jim.
Jim: Thank you, Nico.
Nico: And thanks for following with us.